Glenn Beall Comb Collection
Glenn Beall Comb Collection
1830s-1930s
Beall, Glenn.
4 linear ft.
Collection of antique and modern plastic hair combs.
5279656
Biographical History
Glenn Beall is an engineer, consultant, educator and editor in the fields of plastics design, processing, and education. He owned and operated his own company, Glenn Beall Engineering, Inc., from 1968 to 1993. and holds more than 35 patents. He has lectured, written, and provided consulting on many aspects of plastics design, and has held leadership positions in the Society of Plastics Engineers (SPE) and Society of the Plastics Industry (SPI).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Glenn Beall Comb Collection contains functional and decorative hair combs dating from the mid-19th century to the early 20th. Almost all are compression-molded of hard rubber (also known as vulcanite), although there are a few examples of other materials and techniques. Several have decorations of glass or jet beads. The donor's original identification numbers (for example "Comb, No. 5") are given below, and all descriptions are based on information provided by the donor.
Arrangement of the Collection
Items are physically arranged as appropriate based on size. They are listed in the inventory below in numeric order, both of the donor's original number and internally-assigned ID numbers.
Subject and Genre Headings
Plastics; Beall, Glenn.; Combs -- History.; Combs -- Specimens.; Hair ornaments.; Combs (hair ornaments)
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Glenn Beall, 2019.
Inventory
- Combs
  - Comb, No. 5, 1860-1880; beall_combs_001; India Rubber Comb Company; silver header with vines and flowers; sterling silver bridge, hard rubber fabricated teeth (Oversize 5)
  - Comb, No. 1384, 1860-1880; beall_combs_002; six teeth, curved, with raised dots; gutta percha or hard rubber, compression molded (Oversize 2)
  - Two-tooth comb, No. 1453, circa 1860; beall_combs_003; three black faceted stones (glass or jet) and metal crescent on header, 2 round teeth; black hard rubber?, fabricated (Oversize 2)
  - Nit comb, No. 1473, 1900-1925; beall_combs_004; fine teeth on both sides, "HER MAJESTY" in center; hard rubber?, compression molded (Oversize 2)
  - Comb, No. 1576, 1870-1880; beall_combs_005; India Rubber Comb Company; five teeth, slightly curved header with oval decoration; vulcanite, compression molded (Oversize 2)
  - Back comb, No. 1799, 1900-1920; beall_combs_006; mid-Victorian, decorative swirls/vines with three large black faceted stones; gutta percha?, compression molded with hand-cut teeth (Oversize 1)
  - Hair preserving comb, No. 1862, beall_combs_007; Peterson's Patent Comb Co., Dublin, Ireland; curved wide-spaced teeth; vulcanite (i.e., hard rubber), compression molded, with original box (Oversize 5)
  - Comb, No. 2280, 1860-1880; beall_combs_008; India Rubber Comb Company; completely plain, no decoration; hard rubber, compression molded (Oversize 2)
  - Pair of two-teeth combs, No. 2294, circa 1860s; beall_combs_009; two 2-teeth combs or hairpins, each with three faceted jet beads; hard rubber teeth, fabricated (Oversize 2)
  - Comb, No. 2543, 1880-1910; beall_combs_010; straight header, 7 blunt prongs topped with faceted jet beads, several broken teeth; hard rubber, compression molded with machine-cut teeth (Oversize 2)
  - Comb, No. 2544, 1880-1910; beall_combs_011; straight header, 8 faceted black glass beads; hard rubber, compression molded with machine-cut teeth (Oversize 2)
  - Comb, No. 2690, 1880-1910; beall_combs_012; curved header with small squared-off oval relief decoration; hard rubber, compression molded (Oversize 4)
  - Six-tooth comb, No. 3010, circa 1860s; beall_combs_013; curved header with rod tipped with faceted black beads; hard rubber, fabricated header, compression molded comb (Oversize 1)
  - Three-tooth comb, No. 3011, circa 1860s; beall_combs_014; curved header, round black beads and metal flowers (some have come loose), hinged; hard rubber, fabricated header, compression molded comb (Oversize 5)
  - Four-tooth comb, No. 3012, 1910-1930; beall_combs_015; offset teardrop-shaped header, no decoration; hard rubber, fabricated, originally black but bleached to light tan (Oversize 4)
  - Comb, No. 3013, 1860-1880; beall_combs_016; curved header with curved teardrop-shaped section, reddish-brown; hard rubber, compression molded (Oversize 2)
  - Comb, No. 3014, 1870-1890; beall_combs_017; curved header with 11 raised teardrop shapes, reddish-brown; hard rubber, compression molded (Oversize 4)
  - Comb, No. 3015, 1870-1930; beall_combs_018; curved header with five large oval depressions, dark greenish-brown; hard rubber, compression molded (Oversize 1)
  - Back comb, No. 3522, 1910-1930; beall_combs_019; pierced header with vines/leaves; hard rubber, fabricated from compression molded sheet (Oversize 3)
  - "Revelation" comb, No. 3353, 1903-1905; beall_combs_020; Harburg Rubber Comb Co., Germany; grooming comb, 58 teeth, black; hard rubber, compression molded with original box (Oversize 5)
  - Five-tooth comb, No. 3354, 1880-1910; beall_combs_021; curved header, 9 faceted black beads on small blunt prongs; hard rubber, compression molded (Oversize 3)
  - High back comb, No. 3355, 1890-1930; beall_combs_022; large ornate header, pierced and with relief design; hard rubber, compression molded (Oversize 3)
  - Comb, No. 3356, 1890-1930; beall_combs_023; curved header resembling large chain links, 7 teeth, hinged, brown; hard rubber, fabricated header with compression molded teeth (Oversize 1)
  - Comb, No. 3357, 1890-1930; beall_combs_024; curved horseshoe-shaped header extending to bottom of teeth, 9 faceted black beads (glass or jet), hinged; hard rubber, fabricated and compression molded (Oversize 1)
  - Comb, No. 3358, 1890-1930; beall_combs_025; curved header, spiral-wrapped rod with three round black beads, 20 teeth; hard rubber, fabricated header and compression molded teeth (Oversize 4)
  - Utility comb, No. 3359A, beall_combs_026; 7" grooming comb, fine-tooth at one end, larger at the other end, hot-stamped "ACE" at center, black; hard rubber, compression molded (Oversize 4)
  - Utility comb, No. 3359B, beall_combs_027; 5" grooming comb, fine-tooth at one end, larger at the other end, hot-stamped "ACE" at center, black; hard rubber, compression molded (Oversize 2)
  - Comb, No. 3360, 1870-1930; beall_combs_028; tall header with rounded points resembling a crown, 9 teeth; hard rubber, compression molded (Oversize 1)
  - Back comb, No. 3361, 1890-1920; beall_combs_029; curved header, 7 decorative protrusions resembling top hats, 7 teeth; hard rubber, compression molded (Oversize 3)
  - Back comb, No. 3362, 1890-1920; beall_combs_030; 9-pronged header originally topped with 9 beads (missing when donated), 10 teeth; hard rubber, compression molded (Oversize 5)
  - Back comb, No. 3363, 1880-1910; beall_combs_031; curved header with diagonal ridges and rounded bumps, 7 teeth; hard rubber, compression molded (Oversize 5)